Hi!
I’m Jim Dowd at zoaroutdoor.com.
In 4 part cast, we made our casting movements and our stops and strokes with just the rod hand.
Let me introduce something called the haul with the line hand.
What the haul does is gives a tiny little tug just before you make your forward stroke.
Just a tiny little tug.
And that forces the load of the weight of the fly line into the rod a little more and gives you more acceleration.
It is a wonderful thing to use when there is wind, because it drives your loop faster.
Faster speed translates into greater efficiency; it also contributes to accuracy.
And here’s how you do it.
Just a tiny little tug, just before you make your pop stop.
A tug, tug, tug, tug.
You notice back tug, forward tug.
I am doing them together.
I am using my hands together.
So the haul is something that if you work on 1 at a time, first the back and the forward, will enable you to fish more efficiently and cast farther.